# Shakiba Davari

Email: sdavari@vt.edu Website: s-davari.github.io Green Card Holder

## Research Interest

Intelligent Augmented Reality (AR) Interface Design: My research interest lies in connecting my past research experience in applied machine learning (ML) and my current passion for AR interfaces. I am a 3D interaction/interface designer focusing on intelligent AR interfaces. I concentrate on different aspects of detecting AR users' context and utilizing it to adapt their AR interface. Such context-aware interfaces mitigate the existing challenges of AR, such as real-world occlusion and social intrusiveness, while providing more reliable and efficient information access and interaction in AR.

### Education

Ph.D., Computer Science Expected graduation: Aug 2024

Virginia Tech (2018-Present)

MSc., Computer Science

Specialization: Human-Computer Interaction (Degree received)

Virginia Tech (2018-2020)

Specialization: Computational Perception and Robotics

Georgia Tech (2017-2018)

**BSc.,** Computer Engineering (<u>Degree received</u>)

Shahid Beheshti University(SBU), Iran(2010-2014)

# Research Experience

**Graduate Research Assistant** 

Virginia Tech (2018-Present)

Advisor: Doug A. Bowman

—— Conceptual Framework Research ———



I applied a methodical approach based on a) consideration of end goals, features, and challenges of AR, and b) indepth review and analysis of existing AR interfaces, input modalities, context frameworks, and taxonomies to:

- I proposed a <u>taxonomy of the design dimensions and adaptations</u> of AR interfaces [1].
- I proposed a taxonomy of context tailored for capturing and inferring the intricacies and features crucial to effective intelligent AR interfaces [2, 7].
- I developed a <u>framework</u> for context-aware inference and adaptation towards intelligent AR interfaces [2, 7].
- I proposed a methodology to classify AR interfaces and utilized it to introduce Glanceable AR [8, 9].
- I proposed a guideline for evaluating and comparing AR input modalities and am currently conducting a survey on the natural AR input modalities according to this guideline [3].
  - ———— Socially Intelligent AR Interfaces —
- I designed and developed a socially intelligent AR interface for HoloLens devices, incorporating face and speech recognition to adapt the content and display of the information to the context.
- I designed an experiment to evaluate the effect of AR interfaces and context-awareness on the user experience and information access efficiency compared to mobile phones.
- I conducted a user study on 36 participants, published the results, and presented them at IEEE VR 2022 [6].
  - ———— Teamwork —
- I designed Drill-AR for HoloLens devices to speed up drilling tasks at the Boeing Aircraft Company assembly line.
- I designed and implemented a prototype for an AR Operating System Interface.
- I participated in various teams in the annual 3DUI Contest at the IEEE VR conference.
  - I designed 3D Interaction techniques and communicated our findings through publications, receiving the Best <u>3DUI award</u> for two consecutive years.
  - o I led a team of 10 graduate and undergraduate students to design an immersive VR experience using passive haptics and everyday proxy objects.

Tools: Python, OpenCV, DNNs, Flask web app development, Unity Game Engine, Photon, MRTK

### **Research Scientist Intern**

Adobe Inc. (2022 May-Aug)

- I designed and developed 16 different AR interfaces for content navigation on iOS devices and explored their effectiveness in multiple contexts through a <u>preliminary survey</u>.
- I implemented the most promising candidate interfaces on HoloLens devices.
- I conducted a user study on 24 participants to collect quantitative and qualitative data for evaluating two different AR content placement strategies in four contexts.
- I performed various statistical significance analyses, such as non-parametric ART-ANOVA, on the study data and

detailed the results in a manuscript intended for publication [4].

Tools: Apple ARKit, Swift, Adobe Aero, Unity Game Engine, MRTK, JMP

#### Research Intern

Microsoft Inc. (2021 May-Aug)

- I designed and developed a new tool to leverage the potential of <u>virtual monitors for assisting low-vision users.</u>
- I designed and conducted a user study on 21 low-vision participants.
- I derived valuable <u>design guidelines</u> for enhancing the hardware and software aspects of virtual monitors tailored to the needs of the low-vision population [5].

  Tools: Unity Game Engine

### Researcher

**Stanford University (2017-2018)** 

- I designed and developed <u>driving simulation scenarios</u> to gather driver data across diverse situations in a project Investigating the effect of leveraging human actions in autonomous cars.
- I investigated various algorithms to <u>automate the flight path of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles</u> (UAVs) for efficient image capture within dynamic construction sites. *Tools: SimVista, SimCreator, Python2, OpenCV, Pymunck*

#### Researcher

## **University of Toronto (2015-2016)**

- I combined various ML classification models to develop a robust system that categorizes construction site images into one of the five construction progress stages states indicative of the construction progress [10].
- I automated web crawling and the extraction of reliable data from target websites for an online assistive technology rating system for caregivers.
   Tools: Python2, OpenCV, Selenium, Apache Nutch

### Selected Honors & Awards

Invited Talk: "Context Aware Inference and Adaptation in Intelligent AR Interfaces"

[PERCxR @ISMAR 2022]

Best 3DUI Award

[IEEEVR 2020 & IEEEVR 2021]

Departmental Service Award

[CS Department @Virginia Tech 2020]

Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing Scholarship

[Virginia Tech 2022] – [Virginia Tech 2021]

Inclusion, Diversity, and Accessibility Scholarship

[IEEEVR 2022]

ACM Capital Region Celebration of Women in Computing Scholarship

[Virginia Tech 2020]

Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Scholarship

[Tapia Foundation 2020] – [Virginia Tech 2019] – [Georgia Tech-2017]

## **Selected Service Activities**

Workshop Co-organizer

[1st Workshop on Intelligent XR: Harnessing AI for Next-Generation XR User Experiences (iXR), ISMAR 2024]

Poster Chair

[ACM Spatial User Interaction (SUI) 2024] [CHI 2021 & 2023] – [IEEEVR 2021 & 2022] – [ISMAR 2020 & 2021 & 2022] – [UIST 2022] – [AutomotiveUI 2020]

Reviewer Leadership Roles

[Virginia Tech Graduate Student Council 2019-2020] — [Iranian Society at Virginia Tech 2018 to 2021]

Mentoring and Advising

irginia recir Graduate Student Council 2019-2020] – [iranian Society at Virginia recir 2016 to 2021

[Danny Stover 2022-2023] - [Alexander Giovanelli 2021-2022] - [Daniel Manesh 2021-2022]

### **Publications**

- [1] <u>A Taxonomy of Design Dimensions and Adaptations in AR</u>, <u>S. Davari</u>, DA Bowman, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics(TVCG) 2024 (In-preparation)
- [2] Intelligent AR: A Taxonomy of Context and a Framework for Context-Aware Inference and Adaptation, S. Davari, DA. Bowman, IEEE CG&A Special Issue on Next-generation Mixed-Reality User Experiences (In-preparation)
- [3] An AR Input Modality Evaluation Guideline and A Survey on the Natural Input Modalities in Augmented Reality, S. Davari, Logan Lane, DA. Bowman, IEEE TVCG 2024 (In-preparation)
- [4] <u>Exploring Content Placement Strategies for Context-Aware Augmented Reality, S. Davari, DA Bowman, S. Petrangili, J. Hofswell (under-review)</u>
- [5] <u>Virtual monitors vs. physical monitors: an empirical comparison for productivity work</u>, L. Pavanatto, <u>S. Davari</u>, C. Badea, R. Stoackley, DA. Bowman, Frontiers in Virtual Reality 2023, Vol 4, 1215820
- [6] <u>Validating the Benefits of Glanceable and Context-Aware Augmented Reality for Everyday Information Access Tasks, S. Davari,</u> F. Lu, DA. Bowman, IEEE VR 2022, New Zealand, pp. 436-444
- [7] [DC] Context-Aware Inference and Adaptation in AR, S. Davari, IEEE VR 2022, New Zealand, pp. 938-939
- [8] Occlusion Management Techniques for Everyday Glanceable AR Interfaces, S. Davari, F. Lu, and DA. Bowman, Workshop on Everyday VR (WEVR) @ IEEE VR 2020, USA, pp. 324-330
- [9] <u>Glanceable AR: Evaluating Information Access Methods for Head-Worn Augmented Reality, F. Lu, S. Davari, L. Lisle, Y. Li, DA. Bowman, IEEE VR 2020, Atlanta, GA, USA. pp. 930-938</u>
- [10] <u>Automated computer vision-based detection of components of under-construction indoor partitions,</u> H. Hamledari, B. McCabe, <u>S. Davari</u>, Automation in Construction 2017, Vol 74, pp. 78-94